Guide to the James Wilder Green Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James Wilder Green papers
1950-2003
1958-1976
MS 1891
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
53.5
(19 boxes)
Green, James Wilder
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy T. Park, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
James Wilder Green (1927-2005) was an American architect and arts administrator. He received his bachelor of architecture degree from Yale in 1952. For twenty-five years, he sat on the board of The MacDowell Colony, and was director of the American Federation of the Arts from 1971 to 1987. He was also a longtime staff member at the Museum of Modern Art, beginning in 1956 in the Department of Architecture and Design as assistant to Alfred Barr and becoming head of the Department of Exhibitions from 1967 to 1970.
Scope and Contents
The James Wilder Green papers document Green's architectural commissions from 1950-2003. While Green never worked full-time as an architect, he was trained at Yale by Louis Kahn and apprenticed with Philip Johnson in New York and Paul Rudolph in Florida. His services as a residential and furniture designer were in demand by friends and family, and he also redesigned several galleries and museum exhibition spaces.
Other Finding Aids
For a list of projects and the boxes in which project materials are located, please consult the Project Index.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two series: Series I, Personal Papers, and Series II, Project Records.
Architecture -- 20th Century -- United States; Green, James Wilder; Jewish Museum (New York, N.Y.); Marlborough-Gerson Gallery; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); National Gallery of Art (U.S.)
- Personal Papers, Circa 1952-1967; Series I
  Arrangement
  Items are listed by type of material.
  - Sketchbook, Yale University, Circa 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Teaching: Hunter College, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writing: Green, James Wilder, "Architecture in Theaters" in Chrysalis, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Project Records, 1950-2003; Series II
  Material is arranged alphabetically by project/client name.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of architectural drawings and sketches. The clients for which project materials are contained in the series are listed below. See the attached project index for box numbers and other project information.
  - 180 Beacon St. Corporation Lobby- Gallery-Sculpture Court, 1965
    Job location: Boston, MA
    Project type: Business
    - Drawings (Box 13)
    - Details (Box 13)
  - Angell, Ernest: guest house, 1960
    Job location: Prout's Neck,
    Scarborough, ME
    Project type: Residential
    - Drawings (Box 7)
    - Details (Box 7)
  - Angell, Ernest: main house, 1967-1969
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 14)
  - Auchincloss apartment 3-4 D, 1969
    Job location: 812 Park
    Ave., New York, NY
    Project type: Tube Fixtures
    - Details (Box 1)
  - Bettelheim, Ralph and Mildred Constantine, 1968-1969
    Job location: New York, NY
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Bettelheim, Ralph and Mildred Constantine: addition, 1960
    - Drawings (Box 7)
  - Bettelheim, Ralph and Mildred Constantine: addition, 1965-1966
    - Drawings (Box 14)
  - Blinken, Mr. & Mrs. Donald, 1999
    Job location: East
    Hampton, NY
    Project type: Baffle screen
    - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Byers, J. Frederick apartment, 1969-1971
    Job location: 66 E. 79th
    St., New York, NY
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 16)
  - Carter, Dr. & Mrs. George H.,:cabinet
    Job location: 10 Garden
    Terrace, Cambridge, MA
    Project type: Furniture
    - Drawings (Box 3)
  - Carter, Dr. & Mrs. George H.: alteration
    - Drawings (Box 3)
  - Carter, Dr. & Mrs. George H.: summer cottage, 1958
    Job location: Wareham, NA
    - Drawings (Box 6)
  - Dewey, Mr. & Mrs. F. H. III, 1955
    Job location: Holden, MA
    - Drawings (Box 2)
  - Eastman, Lee V.: alterations, 1962
    Job location: 39 W. 54th
    - Drawings (Box 9)
  - Evans, Mr. & Mrs. Tilghman
    Job location: Quaker Hill,
    Pawling, NY
    - Drawings (Box 18)
  - Green apartment
    - Drawings (Box 19)
  - Green, James Wilder, 1973
    Job location: 519 Old
    Stone Highway, East Hampton, NY
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 19)
  - Green, James Wilder, 1965-1970
    Job location: 169 E. 78th
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 16)
  - Green, James Wilder apartment, 1965
    Job location: 430 E. 57th
    - Drawings (Box 14)
  - Green, James Wilder: Apartment 9G cabinet
    Job location: 20 E. 74th
    - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Green, James Wilder: closet and bookshelves, 1959
    - Drawings (Box 19)
  - Green, James Wilder: couch, 1962
    - Drawings (Box 19)
  - Green, Thomas S.: deck, 1970
    Job location: Worcester, MA
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 19)
  - Hattis, Phyllis: desk, 2003
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Hennegar, Mr. & Mrs. Gilford, 1957-1958
    Job location: Windmill
    Farm, North Castle, Armonk, NY
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 4–5)
    - Details (Box 4)
  - Herter residence
    Job location: Arroya
    Jacono, NM
    - Drawings (Box 18)
  - Herter, Mr. & Mrs. Christian A., Jr.: swimming pool and pavillion, 1973; 1970
    Job location: 2912 Garfield
    Terrace, Washington, D.C.
    - Drawings (Box 19)
  - Herter, Susan C.: proposed house, 1983
    Job location: Santa Fe, NM
    - Drawings (Box 17)
  - Jewish Museum, Friedenberg Medal Display Room, Main Lobby, 1962-1965
    Job location: 1109 5th
    Project type: Museum
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 11)
  - Kendrick, Jack, 1952
    Job location: Auburn, AL
    Collaborator: Paul Rudolph
    (lead architect)
    - Drawings (Box 2)
  - Kunhardt, Mr. & Mrs. Kenneth: summer camp, 1958
    Job location: Squam Lake, NH
    - Drawings (Box 6)
    - Details (Box 6)
  - Landfield house (suburban), 1964
    Job location: New York
    - Drawings (Box 1)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Landfield, Mr. & Mrs. S., 1962
    Job location: W. 246th St.,
    New York, NY
    - Drawings (Box 10)
  - Lowry, Bates apartment, 1968-1969
    Job location: 941 Park
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
  - Luten, Clarey, Stern, Inc. showroom, 1961
    Job location: 1059 3rd
    - Drawings (Box 9)
  - Mabon, Mr. & Mrs. James H., Jr., 1958-1959
    Job location: New Marlborough, MA
    - Drawings (Box 6)
  - Marlborough-Gerson Gallery, 1963-1967
    Job location: 595 Madison
    Photographer: Alexandre Georges
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 11)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Mathews, Mr. & Mrs. Irving, apartment, 1983
    Job location: San Antonio, TX
    - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Mellon, Mrs. Gertrud A, 1965-1968
    Job location: 1035 5th
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 14)
  - Moore, Adrian P., 1964-1970
    Job location: Old Lyme, CT
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 16)
  - Moore, Elizabeth B.: proposed alterations, 1995
    Job location: Essex, CT
    - Drawings (Box 17)
  - Moore, Mrs. Clement, 1976
    - Drawings (Box 17)
  - Moore, Mrs. Clement: alterations, 1963
    - Drawings (Box 11)
  - National Gallery of Art renovation (includes reference blueprints, 1939-1940), 1964-1965
    Job location: Washington, D.C.
    - Drawings (Box 12)
  - Oldenburg, Mr. & Mrs. Richard, 1971-1974
    Job location: Amagansett, NY
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 19)
  - Paley, William S.: offices
    - Drawings (Box 19)
  - Rockefeller, John D.:art storage and workroom, 1964-1965
    Job location: 7 Beekman
    Place, New York, NY
    Project type: Residence, Furniture
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 14)
    - Details (Box 14)
  - Schneider, Karl: planter boxes and shelf, 1994
    Project type: Accessories
    - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Slatkin, Mr. & Mrs. Charles: gallery alterations, 1958
    Job location: 115 E. 92nd
    - Drawings (Box 7)
  - Smith, Mrs. Bertram, 1966-1971
    Job location: 907 5th Ave.,
    - Manuscript Material (Box 1)
    - Drawings (Box 15)
  - Twitchell, Mrs. R. S.: boat and guest house, 1950
    Collaborator: Twitchell &
    Rudolph (architects)
    - Drawings (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1952-1953
    - Drawings (Box 1, Box 19)
    - Photographs (Box 1)
  - White, James P.: table, 1962
    Job location: 40 E. 63rd
    - Drawings (Box 9)
  - Wise, Howard: gallery, 1960
    Job location: 50 W. 54th
    - Drawings (Box 8)
    - Details (Box 8)
  - Zuckerman: desk, table, cabinet, 1992
    - Drawings (Box 1)